Ralph Ellison
Manuscript Division, Library of Congress
- General Correspondence, 1930-1996, n.d. (Box 35-79)
  - Breadloaf Writers' Conference, Middlebury College, Middlebury, Vt., 1958-1960, 1986, n.d.
  - British Broadcasting Corp., 1963-1965, 1975, 1981-1984, n.d.
  - Brooks, Lucille See Container 45, Dillon, Lucille
  - Burke, Kenneth, 1945-1954, 1964-1972, 1981-1985, n.d., (2 folders)
  - "B-Bay" miscellaneous, 1936, 1948-1993, n.d., (3 folders)
  - "Be-Bo" miscellaneous, 1937-1994, n.d., (7 folders) (Box 39)
  - "Br-By" miscellaneous, 1937-1993, n.d., (5 folders) (Box 40)
  - Calicutt, Harold, 1940-1952, 1971-1975, n.d.
  - Callahan, John F., Susan, Eve, and Sasha, 1977-1995, n.d., (2 folders)
  - Carleton College, Northfield, Minn., 1965-1972, 1981-1982, 1988-1989, n.d., (2 folders) (Box 41)
  - Cayton, Horace R., 1945-1947, 1957-1970, n.d.
  - Cheever, John and Mary, 1958-1964, n.d.
  - Cherne, Leo and Phyllis, 1953-1958, 1970, 1976, 1985-1992, n.d.
  - Chute, Marchette Gaylord and Joy, 1956-1976, 1986, n.d.
  - Ciardi, John, 1956, 1962-1964, 1981-1988
  - Clark, Kenneth Bancroft and Mamie, 1955-1963, 1970-1976, 1982-1987, n.d., (2 folders)
  - Coe College, Cedar Rapids, Iowa, 1960-1969, 1983
  - Columbia University, New York, N.Y., 1953-1983, 1990-1993, n.d., (2 folders)
  - Congress for Cultural Freedom, 1956-1966, n.d.
  - Copeland, Virginia, 1957, 1984-1994, n.d. (Box 42)
  - Covo, Jacqueline, 1953-1957, 1964, 1971-1975, n.d., (2 folders)
  - Crouch, Stanley, 1971, 1977-1989, n.d.
  - Curry, Frances and Jimmy, 1954-1957, 1975-1976, n.d.
  - "Ca" miscellaneous, 1950-1994, n.d., (4 folders)
  - "Ce-Com" miscellaneous, 1942-1994, n.d., (7 folders) (Box 43)
  - "Con-Cu" miscellaneous, 1943-1993, n.d., (3 folders) (Box 44)
  - Dartmouth College, Hanover, N.H., 1962-1969, 1976, 1983-1988
  - Davidson, Charles, 1962-1977, n.d.
  - Davis, Henry B. O. ("Hoolie"), 1984-1985
  - Dawson, William L., 1933-1934, 1954-1988, n.d., (2 folders)
  - DeCredico, Jessan, 1980-1990
  - Deren, Maya, 1948-1954, n.d.
  - Detroit Institute of Arts, Detroit, Mich., 1986-1987
  - Dial Press, 1954-1971 (Box 45)
  - Diamond, David, 1968, 1987, n.d.
  - Dillon, Lucille, 1945-1959, n.d.
  - Doubleday and Co., 1943-1946, 1958-1982
  - Douglas, Jean, 1952-1957, n.d.
  - Drye, F. L., 1935
  - Ducornet, Guy, 1960-1962, n.d.
  - "Da-Di" miscellaneous, 1937-1994, n.d., (5 folders)
  - "Do-Dy" miscellaneous, 1942-1994, n.d., (3 folders) (Box 46)
  - Edel, Leon, 1976, 1986-1987
  - Educational Services, 1964-1965
  - Ellington, Duke, n.d. See Oversize
  - Engle, Paul, and Hualing Nieh, 1945, 1955-1991, n.d., (3 folders)
  - Esquire, 1949, 1958-1981, 1987, 1994, n.d., (2 folders) (Box 47)
  - "E" miscellaneous, 1934, 1952-1954, 1961-1994, n.d., (4 folders)
  - Fabre, Michel, 1970-1973, 1983, 1989, n.d.
  - Faulkner, William, 1956-1957, n.d.
  - Fisk University, Nashville, Tenn., 1949-1953, 1963-1966, n.d.
  - Ford, Harry, 1947, 1955-1956, n.d.
  - Forrest, Leon and Anne, 1972-1981, 1987-1988, n.d. (Box 48)
  - Frank, Joseph, 1964-1975, 1981-1986, n.d.
  - "F" miscellaneous, 1937-1940, 1948-1994, n.d., (5 folders)
  - Golsan, Lucy, 1978-1980 (Box 49)
  - Grapevine Gallery, Oklahoma City, Okla., 1976-1996, n.d., (2 folders)
  - Gray, Walter L., Jr. See same container, Grapevine Gallery
  - Grinnell College, Grinnell, Iowa, 1967
  - Guggenheimer, Ida E., 1944-1959, n.d.
  - "Ga-Go" miscellaneous, 1944-1994, n.d., (3 folders)
  - "Gr-Gy" miscellaneous, 1948-1994, n.d., (3 folders) (Box 50)
  - Hagopian, Sylvia der See Container 71, Tamm, Sylvia
  - Hanes, R. Philip, 1966-1981, 1987, n.d.
  - Harper, Michael S., 1971-1976, 1982-1994, n.d.
  - Harper and Row Publishers, 1953-1969, 1977-1980, 1987, n.d.
  - Harper's Magazine, 1943, 1949-1953, 1960-1968, 1990, n.d.
  - Harrison, Hazel, 1936-1940, 1954, 1967-1969, n.d.
  - Harvard University, Cambridge, Mass., 1962-1993, n.d., (2 folders)
  - Healy, Arthur and Sophia, 1959-1969, n.d. (Box 51)
  - Hebestreit, Ludwig, n.d.
  - Hemingway, Mary, 1964-1978, n.d.
  - Hersey, John and Barbara, 1971-1974, 1980-1987, n.d.
  - Hicks, Elizabeth, 1954-1962, 1974, 1988, n.d.
  - Hines, Odette Harper, 1974, 1984-1987
  - Honsaker, Debbie and Coy, 1971, 1977-1992, n.d.
  - Houghton Mifflin Co., 1944-1947, 1966-1970, 1976-1980, 1987-1993, n.d.
  - Howard, Marie Toynet, 1935-1938
  - Howard University, Washington, D.C., 1954, 1964-1967, 1977-1987, n.d.
  - Howe, Irving, 1976-1981, 1988, n.d.
  - Hughes, Langston, 1936-1966, n.d.
  - Humphrey, Hubert H., 1966-1968
  - Hyman, Stanley Edgar, and Shirley Jackson, 1942-1972, 1986, n.d., (2 folders)
  - "Ha-Hs" miscellaneous, 1934, 1940-1994, n.d., (10 folders) (Box 52)
  - "Hu-Hy" miscellaneous, 1954-1994, n.d., (2 folders) (Box 53)
  - "I" miscellaneous, 1940, 1949-1993, n.d., (3 folders)
  - Jackson, Shirley See Container 51, Hyman, Stanley Edgar
  - John Simon Guggenheim Memorial Foundation, 1944-1945, 1954-1989, n.d., (2 folders)
  - Johnson, Lyndon B. and Lady Bird, 1965-1979, 1986, n.d.
  - Julius Rosenwald Fund, 1944-1946, n.d.
  - "J" miscellaneous, 1935-1993, n.d., (5 folders) (Box 54)
  - Katz, Donald, 1972-1989, n.d.
  - Kazin, Alfred, 1947, 1954-1955, 1987
  - Kostelanetz, Richard, 1964-1992, n.d.
  - Kouwenhoven, John Atlee, 1970-1988
  - "K" miscellaneous, 1950-1994, n.d., (5 folders) (Box 55)
  - Langston University, Langston, Okla., 1953, 1966-1970, 1978, 1985
  - Lazenberry, Joe, 1935-1939, n.d.
  - Lee, Edd and Betty Allen, 1958-1964, 1974-1975, 1985-1988, n.d.
  - Lerner, Max and Edna, 1955-1957, 1968, n.d.
  - Lewis, Richard W. B. and Nancy, 1954-1970, 1977-1991, n.d.
  - Lillard, Stewart, Jr., 1967-1989, n.d.
  - Lynes, Russell and Mildred, 1955-1956, 1970-1987, n.d.
  - "L" miscellaneous, 1936-1941, 1952-1994, n.d., (6 folders) (Box 56)
  - MacLeish, Archibald, 1956-1957, n.d.
  - Macmillan Co., 1957, 1963-1974, 1980, n.d.
  - Mann, Augusta and Sam, 1948-1958, 1964-1972, 1979-1984, n.d.
  - Martin, David, 1952-1953, 1971-1974, n.d. (Box 57)
  - Mazzetti, Annamarie and Mario, 1957-1965, n.d.
  - McGraw-Hill Book Co., 1953-1972, 1983-1984, n.d.
  - McPherson, James Alan, 1956, 1969-1994, n.d., (3 folders)
  - Middlebury College, Middlebury, Vt., 1958-1971
  - Miller, Lucille See Container 45, Dillon, Lucille
  - Moore, Julia A. ("Chubby"), 1933-1938
  - Morisey, Alexander, 1934, 1943-1968, 1979-1980, 1987-1992, n.d., (2 folders)
  - Murray, Albert, and Murray family, 1947-1962, 1967-1970, 1978-1988, n.d., (2 folders) (Box 58)
  - "Ma" miscellaneous, 1941-1994, n.d., (5 folders)
  - "Mc-Mo" miscellaneous, 1932, 1942-1994, n.d., (8 folders) (Box 59)
  - "Mr-My" miscellaneous, 1953-1976, 1982-1993, n.d. (Box 60)
  - Nadel, Alan, 1984-1991
  - Naguid, Jack and Nina, 1937-1938, n.d.
  - National Educational Television and Radio Center, 1965-1966
  - Negro Quarterly, 1940-1945, 1968, n.d., (2 folders)
  - New Masses, 1939-1947, n.d.
  - New York Times, 1953-1955, 1963-1987
  - New Yorker, 1945-1960, 1966, 1976-1978, n.d.
  - Newsweek, 1963-1966, 1974, 1992
  - Nieh, Hualing See Container 46, Engel, Paul
  - Norman, Dorothy and Edward, 1948-1959, 1965-1966, 1976, n.d.
  - "N" miscellaneous, 1938-1993, n.d., (8 folders) (Box 61)
  - Oklahoma Heritage Association, Hall of Fame, 1986, 1992, n.d. (Box 62)
  - O'Meally, Robert G., 1973-1988, (2 folders)
  - Organization of American Historians, 1971-1972, n.d.
  - "O" miscellaneous, 1936, 1943-1994, n.d., (4 folders)
  - Paris Review, 1954-1967, 1980-1984, n.d.
  - Partisan Review, 1952-1966, 1983, n.d.
  - Peterson, Renee and William, 1950-1952, n.d. (Box 63)
  - Playboy, 1962, 1981, n.d.
  - Po, Pansy, 1968-1993, n.d., (2 folders)
  - Porter, Horace, 1976-1992, n.d., (2 folders)
  - Princeton University, Princeton, N.J., 1952-1983, n.d., (3 folders)
  - Pushcart Book Press, 1975-1983
  - "P" miscellaneous, 1936-1993, n.d., (7 folders) (Box 64)
  - "Q" miscellaneous, 1957, 1963-1969, 1976-1977, n.d.
  - Ralph Ellison Branch, Metropolitan Library System, Oklahoma City, Okla., 1973-1990, n.d., (2 folders) See also Oversize (Box 65)
  - Rampersad, Arnold, 1980-1988
  - Randolph, James and Madeline, 1953, 1966-1982, n.d.
  - Random House, 1947-1994, n.d., (2 folders)
  - Rhone, Camille and Mamie, 1954-1955, 1985-1986
  - Roark, James L., 1980-1986
  - Roche, Connie and John, 1971, 1977-1992, n.d.
  - Rockefeller Foundation, 1964-1980, n.d.
  - "R" miscellaneous, 1939-1994, n.d., (9 folders) (Box 66)
  - Sarser, David and Gloria, 1955-1969, 1975-1982, 1989-1990, n.d. (Box 67)
  - Saturday Evening Post, 1963-1966, n.d.
  - Saturday Review, 1952-1962, 1982
  - Schiwetz, Berthold ("Tex"), 1956-1971, n.d.
  - Schwartz, Bernard Lee and Ronny, 1978-1983, n.d.
  - Scott, Nathan A. and Charlotte, 1961-1995, n.d, (4 folders)
  - Slaughter, Edna, 1954-1969, n.d.
  - Smith, William Jay, 1959, 1970, 1977-1992
  - Smithsonian Institution, Washington, D.C., 1966-1990, n.d. (Box 68)
  - Spence, Muriel, 1982-1987, n.d.
  - Sprague, Morteza D., 1943, 1952-1967, n.d.
  - State Department, 1937, 1955, 1963-1967, 1974-1975
  - State University of New York, Albany, N.Y., and other locations, 1963-1984, n.d.
  - Stavis, Barrie, 1982-1988
  - Steegmuller, Francis, and Steegmuller family, 1947-1958, 1971, 1979-1986, 1994, n.d.
  - Stein, Edwin and Gretchen, 1947-1959, 1979, n.d.
  - Stepto, Robert B., 1976-1984
  - Stern, Richard, and family, 1960-1968, 1975, n.d.
  - Stevens, Roger L. and Christine, 1970, 1976-1978, 1989-1993, n.d.
  - Steveson, Vivian E., 1931-1936, 1964, 1991, n.d., (4 folders) (Box 69)
  - Stewart, James E., 1972-1992, n.d.
  - Stokowski, Leopold, 1969-1970
  - "S-Sc" miscellaneous, 1943, 1952-1993, n.d., (3 folders)
  - "Se-Sp" miscellaneous, 1937-1995, n.d., (9 folders) (Box 70)
  - "St-Sz" miscellaneous, 1937-1994, n.d., (6 folders) (Box 71)
  - Tamm, Sylvia, 1958-1970, n.d.
  - Tate, Ethel, 1936
  - Taylor, Frank E., 1944-1950, 1959-1964, 1976, n.d.
  - Tomorrow, 1943-1944
  - Tuskegee Institute, Tuskegee, Ala., 1952-1989
  - "T" miscellaneous, 1937-1946, 1952-1994, n.d., (7 folders) (Box 72)
  - Ullian, Edith and Lew, 1954-1956, n.d.
  - University of California, Berkeley, Calif., and other locations, 1957, 1963-1989 (Box 73)
  - University of Chicago, Chicago, Ill., 1959-1980, n.d.
  - University of Michigan, Ann Arbor, Mich., 1966-1969, 1977, 1983, n.d.
  - University of Mississippi, University, Miss., 1976-1987
  - University of North Carolina, Chapel Hill, N.C., and other locations, 1962-1970, 1979-1983, n.d.
  - University of Notre Dame, Notre Dame, Ind., 1965-1973, n.d.
  - University of Wisconsin, Madison, Wis., and other locations, 1963-1972, 1978, n.d.
  - "U" miscellaneous, 1953-1993, n.d., (7 folders) (Box 74)
  - Van Lanschot, W.C.J.M. ("Bib"), 1956-1958, n.d. (Box 75)
  - Viking Press, 1945, 1954-1969, n.d.
  - "V" miscellaneous, 1944-1945, 1954-1983, 1989-1991, n.d., (2 folders)
  - Warren, Robert Penn, 1953-1990, n.d.
  - Weaver, Edith and Richard, 1952-1967, n.d.
  - Weisberg, Bernard and Lois, 1962-1968, 1975-1980, 1988, n.d.
  - Wesleyan University, Middletown, Conn., 1962-1966, 1974-1977, 1986
  - Whitby, Malcolm, 1930-1949, n.d.
  - Whittaker, Joseph, 1971-1977, n.d.
  - Wiig, Francesca, 1967-1981, n.d.
  - Wilbur, Charlee and Richard, 1962-1987, n.d.
  - William Morris Agency
    - 1943, 1953-1955, 1964-1968
    - 1969-1993, n.d. (Box 76)
  - Williams, Walter B., 1934-1944, n.d.
  - Wilson, Ed, 1974-1990, n.d.
  - Wright, John S., 1981-1991, n.d.
  - Wright, Richard and Ellen, 1937-1953, n.d., (2 folders)
  - Wright, Thew and Kit, 1966-1971, 1984, 1990-1991, n.d.
  - "W-Wk" miscellaneous, 1936-1994, n.d., (8 folders) (Box 77)
  - "Wm-Wy" miscellaneous, 1940-1994, n.d., (3 folders) (Box 78)
  - "X-Y" miscellaneous, 1938, 1947-1994, n.d.
  - "Z" miscellaneous, 1940, 1960-1978, 1986-1990, n.d.
  - Unidentified
    - 1933-1969, (5 folders)
    - 1970-1995, n.d., (5 folders) (Box 79)
- Organizations File, 1939-1994, n.d. (Box 80-94)
  Correspondence, reports, and printed matter relating to Ellison's participation in professional and social organizations as an officer, trustee, or advisor.
  Arranged alphabetically by name of organization and chronologically therein.
  - American Academy and Institute of Arts and Letters, New York, N.Y. (Box 80)
    - 1964-1994, (6 folders)
    - Undated, (2 folders) (Box 81)
  - American Academy in Rome, Rome, Italy, 1955-1960, 1971-1986, 1992-1994, n.d.
  - American Committee for Cultural Freedom, 1956
  - American Revolution Bicentennial Commission, 1967-1969, 1976, n.d.
  - American Scholar, 1955, 1961-1969, 1976-1981, n.d.
  - Associated Councils of the Arts, 1965-1974, n.d.
  - Association of American Publishers, 1979
  - Authors Guild, 1963-1973, 1984-1986, n.d.
  - Authors League of America, 1939, 1974-1975, 1985-1988
  - Bennington College, Bennington, Vt., 1955-1959, 1967-1977, 1982-1989, 1994, n.d., (2 folders)
  - Brandeis University, Waltham, Mass., Creative Arts Awards, 1971-1972, n.d. (Box 82)
  - Carnegie Commission on Educational Television, 1965-1968, n.d., (2 folders)
  - Cathedral Church of St. John the Divine, New York, N.Y., 1987-1993, n.d.
  - Century Association
    - 1954, 1964-1994, (5 folders)
    - Undated, (2 folders) (Box 83)
  - Citizens Committee for Peace with Freedom in Vietnam, 1967-1968, n.d.
  - Citizens for Humphrey, 1963-1968, n.d., (2 folders)
  - Colonial Williamsburg Foundation
    - 1968-1976, (4 folders)
    - 1977-1994, n.d., (7 folders) (Box 84)
  - Commission on Negro History and Culture, 1967-1968, n.d. (Box 85)
  - Coordinating Council of Literary Magazines, 1975-1982, 1988-1990, n.d.
  - Educational Broadcasting Corp., 1968-1979, n.d.
  - Educational Development Center, Newton, Mass., 1968, 1974
  - Fellowship of Southern Writers, 1988-1993
  - Ford Foundation, 1958-1972, 1979, 1984, n.d.
  - Foundation for the Arts, Religion, and Culture, 1962-1970, n.d.
  - Franklin Delano Roosevelt Centennial Commission, 1981-1984, n.d.
  - Franklin Library, 1976-1986, n.d., (2 folders)
  - Hampshire College, Amherst, Mass., 1967-1988, n.d. (Box 86)
  - Harlem School of the Arts, New York, N.Y., 1980-1993, n.d.
  - Holy Land Conservation Fund, 1972-1973, n.d.
  - Hudson Institute, Croton-on-Hudson, N.Y., 1970-1975, 1982-1991
  - Institute for Natural Philosophy, Princeton, N.J., 1979-1981
  - Institute of Jazz Studies, New York, N.Y., 1953-1955
  - International Rescue Committee, 1951, 1964-1994, n.d., (4 folders)
  - John D. and Catherine T. MacArthur Foundation, 1962-1992, n.d., (2 folders) (Box 87)
  - John F. Kennedy Center for the Performing Arts, Washington, D.C., 1965-1976, 1987, n.d., (2 folders)
  - League of American Writers, 1939-1942, n.d.
  - Library of Congress, 1962-1976, 1982-1983, n.d., (2 folders) See also Container 100, "Hidden Name and Complex Fate"
  - Meharry Medical College Fund, 1977-1984, n.d.
  - Metropolitan Museum of Art, New York, N.Y., 1975-1993, n.d., (2 folders) (Box 88)
  - Modern Language Association of America, 1965-1976, 1983-1992
  - Museum of African Art, Washington, D.C., 1963-1987, n.d.
  - Museum of Broadcasting, New York, N.Y., 1979-1980, n.d.
  - Museum of Modern Art, New York, N.Y., 1964-1967, 1975, n.d.
  - Museum of the City of New York, New York, N.Y., 1970-1994, n.d.
  - NAACP
    - ca. 1942, 1954-1955, 1961-1971, (2 folders)
    - 1972-1994, n.d., (2 folders) (Box 89)
  - National Book Foundation
    - 1953-1976, 1988-1989, (6 folders)
    - 1990-1992, n.d. (Box 90)
  - National Citizens' Committee for Public Television, 1967-1974, n.d.
  - National Council on the Arts, 1964-1989, n.d., (4 folders)
  - National Endowment for the Arts, 1966, 1975-1992, n.d., (2 folders)
  - National Endowment for the Humanities, 1972-1980, n.d., (2 folders) (Box 91)
  - National Medical Fellowships, 1984, n.d.
  - National Negro Congress, 1940, n.d.
  - National Portrait Gallery, Washington, D.C., 1972-1978, 1984
  - New School for Social Research, New York, N.Y., 1965-1988, n.d., (6 folders)
  - New York Public Library, New York, N.Y., 1947, 1953, 1966-1992, n.d., (3 folders) (Box 92)
  - Newport Jazz Festival, Newport, R.I., 1955-1958, n.d.
  - Oklahoma Ambassador Corps, Oklahoma City, Okla., 1966-1969, 1990
  - Ossabaw Foundation, 1971-1982, n.d.
  - P.E.N.
    - 1952-1958, (2 folders)
    - 1959-1992, n.d., (4 folders) (Box 93)
  - Rutgers University, New Brunswick, N.J., 1965-1972, n.d.
  - Society for the Arts, Religion, and Contemporary Culture, 1965-1972, 1983, n.d.
  - University of California, La Jolla, Calif., and other locations, 1975-1982, n.d.
  - Wake Forest University, Winston-Salem, N.C., 1964, 1972-1989, n.d., (2 folders)
  - WNET/Thirteen, New York, N.Y., 1968-1986, 1992-1993, n.d., (4 folders) (Box 94)
  - Yale University, New Haven, Conn., 1964-1988, n.d., (3 folders)
- Writings File, 1935-1995, n.d. (Box 95-169)
  Drafts of essays, novels, reviews, short stories, and other material written by Ellison. Correspondence and material relating to the production, publicity, and reception of his works are included. Dates in parentheses in the container list refer to the publication date; other dates refer to the period covered by the material in the folder.
  Arranged alphabetically by type of work and alphabetically by title therein.
  - Essays and essay collections (Box 95)
    - "Adventures of an Unintentional New Yorker," n.d.
    - "The American Artist and His Audience" (1977), 1994
    - American Civilization: a Portrait from the Twentieth Century (1972), unpublished chapter, 1968-1970
    - American Negro Congress, ca. 1940
    - "The Art of Fiction: An Interview," 1970
    - "As the Spirit Moves Mahalia," 1958, 1969
    - Author's statement, Attacks of Taste, 1971
    - "Camp Lost Colony," 1940
    - "Change the Joke and Slip the Yoke"
      - Correspondence, drafts, and partial drafts, 1957, n.d.
      - Draft fragments, n.d.
      - Notes, n.d.
    - "The Charlie Christian Story," 1958
    - "Charlie Houston," n.d.
    - "A Congress Jim Crow Didn't Attend," 1940
    - "The Constitution as Ground or Scene for the Enactment of the Drama of American Democracy," n.d.
    - Down Home, with Bob Adelman, 1969-1972, n.d.
    - Editorial comments
      - General, ca. 1937, 1970, n.d.
      - Negro Quarterly, 1942-1944, n.d., (2 folders) (Box 96)
    - "February" (1955), ca. 1937-1938, 1955, n.d.
    - "Flamenco," 1954
    - Going to the Territory (1986)
      - "An Extravagance of Laughter" See also Container 99, "Going to the Territory," and Container 103, "New York, 1936"
        - First draft, ca. 1985
        - Edited draft, 1985
        - Partial drafts, ca. 1985
        - Work folder, ca. 1985, (2 folders) (Box 97)
      - Contract, 1984
      - Correspondence, 1984-1987, n.d.
      - Printer's setting copy, 1986, (3 folders)
      - Galleys (Box 98)
        - Author's edited version, 1986, (2 folders)
        - Master set
          - First pass, 1986, (3 folders)
          - Second pass, 1986, (3 folders) (Box 99)
      - Inscriptions and mailing lists, 1986-1987, n.d.
      - Miscellany, 1985-1987, n.d.
      - Reviews, 1986-1987, n.d.
    - "Going to the Territory," Carleton Miscellany: A Review of Literature and the Liberal Arts, 1980 See also Containers 96-97, Going to the Territory, "An Extravagance of Laughter"
    - "The Golden Age, Time Past" (1959), 1958-1961, 1972, 1983, n.d.
    - "Harlem Is Nowhere" (1964), 1947-1948, n.d., (3 folders) (Box 100)
    - "Harlem Twenty-Four Hours After--Peace and Quiet Reign," 1943
    - Hemingway, Ernest, unfinished essay, ca. 1940
    - The hero in literature, n.d.
    - "Hidden Name and Complex Fate: A Writer's Experience in the U.S.," 1964 See also Container 87, Library of Congress
    - "Homage to Duke Ellington on His Birthday" (1969), 1969-1970
    - "Imprisoned in Words," 1946-1947, n.d.
    - "Indivisible Man" (1970), 1970-1973, n.d. (Box 101)
    - "James Armistead Lafayette" (1974), 1974-1976, n.d.
    - "Let Us Consider the Harlem Crime Wave," ca. 1943
    - "The Little Man at Chehaw Station" (1977)
      - Drafts and partial drafts, n.d., (2 folders)
      - Miscellany, 1976-1978, n.d.
    - "Living with Music," 1955
    - "Minority Provincialism as a Problem in Creative Writing," n.d.
    - Miscellaneous notes, 1943, 1953-1991, n.d., (6 folders) (Box 102)
    - "The Myth of the Flawed White Southerner" (1968), 1967-1969, n.d. (Box 103)
    - New American left wing writers, ca. 1935
    - "New York, 1936," 1936 See also Containers 96-97, Going to the Territory, "An Extravagance of Laughter"
    - "Notes on the American Language and Literature"
      - Drafts and draft fragments, 1970, n.d., (4 folders)
      - Notes and research material, 1970, n.d. (Box 104)
    - "The Novel as a Function of American Democracy" (1967), 1967, n.d.
    - "On Becoming a Writer" (1965), 1964-1965
    - On Being Black: Writings By Afro-Americans from Frederick Douglass to the Present, 1970
    - "On Being the Target of Discrimination," 1989
    - "On Birdwatching Bird and Jazz" (1962), 1962, n.d.
    - "Perspective of Literature" (1976), 1976-1977
    - "Philippine Writers Report," 1941
    - "Ralph Ellison: Notre Lutte Nous Proclamé à la Fois 'Nègres et Americains,'" Preuves (1958), 1957, 1969
    - "Recent Negro Fiction" (1941), 1941, n.d., (2 folders)
    - "Rejoiner" (1964) See also Container 108, "The World and the Jug"
      - Drafts and draft fragments, n.d.
      - Miscellany, 1964-1969, n.d.
      - Notes, n.d.
    - "Remembering Jimmy," 1958
    - "Remembering Richard Wright" (1984), 1983-1984, n.d. See also Container 174, Lectures, 1971, 18 July (Box 105)
    - "Richard Wright and Negro Fiction," 1941
    - "Richard Wright's Blues" (1945), 1945, n.d.
      - Drafts and partial drafts
      - Draft fragments and notes
    - "Romare Bearden: Paintings and Projections" (1970), 1969-1970, 1985
    - "The Shadow and the Act" (1949), 1949-1950, n.d.
    - Shadow and Act (1964)
      - Contracts, 1964-1968
      - Correspondence, 1964-1978
      - Drafts
        - "Introduction," n.d.
        - "An American Dilemma: A Review," 1944, n.d.
        - "Twentieth Century Fiction and the Black Mask of Humanity," ca. 1946, 1953 (Box 106)
        - Miscellaneous text, 1964-1966, n.d.
      - Miscellany, 1964-1967, 1995, n.d.
      - Reviews, 1964-1967, n.d.
      - Royalty statements, 1966-1974
    - "Society, Morality, and the Novel," The Living Novel (1957), 1956-1963, n.d., (3 folders)
    - "Speaking for You: Ralph Ellison's Cultural Vision" (1987), 1981-1988 See also Container 171, Speeches, 1975, 21 June
    - "The Swing to Stereo," 1958
    - "Tape, Disks, and Coexistence," ghostwritten by Ellison, 1955 (Box 107)
    - "Tell It Like It Is, Baby" (1965)
      - Drafts, 1965-1969, 1990, n.d., (4 folders)
      - Galleys, notes, and general material, 1965-1969, 1990, n.d.
    - "Three Southern Novels," 1944, n.d.
    - "Twentieth Century Writing and the Black Mask of Humanity" (1953), 1946, 1953 See also Container 172, Lectures, 1953, 3-5 Aug.
    - Unidentified fragments, n.d., (2 folders) (Box 108)
    - "The Uses of History in Fiction," with William Styron, Robert Penn Warren, and C. Vann Woodward, 1969 See also Container 170, Speeches, 1968, 6 Nov.
    - "The Way It Is," 1942
    - "What America Would Be Like Without Blacks," 1970, (2 folders)
    - "What's Wrong with the American Novel?" 1955
    - "When Does a Black Join the Middle Class? 'Not When He Has a Good Paying Job,'" 1975
    - "The World and the Jug" (1963) See also Container 104, "Rejoiner"
      - Correspondence, 1963-1964, n.d.
      - Drafts and draft fragments, n.d.
      - Notes, n.d.
  - Forewords, introductions, and endorsements (Box 109)
    - Crane, Stephen, The Red Badge of Courage, 1959-1961, 1988, n.d., (3 folders)
    - General, 1953-1974, 1981, 1990, n.d.
    - Kouwenhoven, John Atlee, The Beer Can by the Highway, 1987-1988, n.d.